Preliminary guide to the Montana Highway Patrol Division records 1950-2002
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Highway Patrol Division records
1950-2002
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 mhslibrary@mt.gov
B8:2-1;B0:9-4
Montana. Highway Patrol Division.
25 linear feet of shelf space
Records of the Montana Highway Patrol Division consist of interoffice correspondence (1953-1977); outgoing correspondence of the Safety Officer (1950-1954); outgoing "headquarters" correspondence (1970-1971, 1977-1985); general correspondence (1989-1990, 1992-2002); minutes of detachment meetings (1993-1001); and subject files (1953-1976, 1987). The headquarters offices represented are the Chief Administrator, Assistant Chief Administrator, Field Force Bureau, Personnel and Training Bureau, Planning and Research Officer, Safety and Education Officer, Personnel Assistant, and Chief Pilot. Some correspondence files include monthly and quarterly reports. The subject files include Indian reservations, the Montana Association of Highway Patrolmen (including minutes), the Montana Highway Patrol Board, an organizational chart, the state governor, and the state highways department.
by series
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Traffic police--Montana.
Montana--Politics and government.
Montana
Transportation
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Interoffice correspondence
  - Bulletins, 1953-1965 (Box-folder 1 / 1-5)
  - Directives, 1966-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 6-12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1972 (Box-folder 1 / 13-14)
- Outgoing correspondence
  - Safety officer, 1950-1954 (Box-folder 2 / 1-5)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1970 (Box-folder 2 / 6-11)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 3 / 1-6)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4 / 1-14)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 5 / 1-16)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 6 / 1-18)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1981-1984 (Box-folder 7 / 1-42)
  - Headquarters correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 8 / 1-12)
- General correspondence
  - Chief Administrator, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8 / 13)
  - Assistant Chief Administrator, 1988 (Box-folder 8 / 14)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1987 (Box-folder 8 / 15)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8 / 16)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Planning and Research Officer, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8 / 17)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Safety and Education Officer, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 8 / 18)
  - Chief Administrator, 1989 (Box-folder 8 / 19)
  - Assistant Chief Administrator, 1989 (Box-folder 8 / 20)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1989 (Box-folder 8 / 21)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1989 (Box-folder 8 / 22-29)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1989 (Box-folder 9 / 1-4)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Planning and Research Officer, 1989 (Box-folder 9 / 5)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Safety and Education Officer, 1989 (Box-folder 9 / 6-7)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1989 (Box-folder 9 / 8)
  - Pilot, 1989 (Box-folder 9 / 9)
  - Chief Administrator, 1990 (Box-folder 9 / 10-11)
  - Assistant Chief Administrator, 1990 (Box-folder 9 / 12)
  - Communications / Planning Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1990 (Box-folder 9 / 13)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1990 (Box-folder 9 / 14-15)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1990 (Box-folder 9 / 16-27)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Safety and Education Officer, 1990 (Box-folder 10 / 1)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1990 (Box-folder 10 / 2)
  - Pilot, 1990 (Box-folder 10 / 3)
  - Chief Administrator, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 4-5)
  - Assistant Chief Administrator, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 6)
  - Communications Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 7)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 8-9)
  - Fleet and Supply Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 10)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 12-22)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Safety and Education Officer, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 23-24)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Training and Research Officer, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 25-26)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1992 (Box-folder 10 / 27)
  - Chief Administrator, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 1-2)
  - Assistant Chief Administrator, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 3)
  - Inspector, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 4)
  - Communications Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 5)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 6-7)
  - Fleet and Supply Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 8)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 9-20)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Safety and Education Officer, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 21)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Training and Research Officer, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 22-23)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Personnel Assistant, 1993 (Box-folder 11 / 24)
  - Chief Administrator, 1994 (Box-folder 12 / 1-2)
  - Assistant Chief Administrator, 1994 (Box-folder 12 / 3)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1994 (Box-folder 12 / 4-5)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1994 (Box-folder 12 / 6-13)
  - Personnel and Training Bureau: Personnel Assistant, 1994 (Box-folder 12 / 14-20)
  - Planning and Research Officer, 1994 (Box-folder 12 / 21-22)
  - Safety and Education, 1994 (Box-folder 12 / 23)
  - Chief Administrator, 1995 (Box-folder 13 / 1-12)
  - Deputy Chief, 1995 (Box-folder 13 / 13-24)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Commander, 1995 (Box-folder 13 / 25-36)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 1995 (Box-folder 13 / 37-48)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 1995 (Box-folder 13 / 49-57)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1995 (Box-folder 13 / 58-69)
  - Chief Administrator, 1996 (Box-folder 14 / 1-12)
  - Deputy Chief, 1996 (Box-folder 14 / 13-23)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Commander, 1996 (Box-folder 14 / 24-36)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1996 (Box-folder 14 / 37-48)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 1996 (Box-folder 14 / 49-57)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1996 (Box-folder 14 / 58-69)
  - Chief Administrator, 1997 (Box-folder 15 / 1-12)
  - Deputy Chief, 1997 (Box-folder 15 / 13-23)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Commander, 1997 (Box-folder 15 / 24-35)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1997 (Box-folder 15 / 36-47)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 1997 (Box-folder 15 / 48-59)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1997 (Box-folder 15 / 60-71)
  - Chief Administrator, 1998 (Box-folder 16 / 1-12)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Commander, 1998 (Box-folder 16 / 13-24)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1998 (Box-folder 16 / 25-36)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 1998 (Box-folder 16 / 37-48)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1998 (Box-folder 16 / 49-60)
  - Chief Administrator, 1999 (Box-folder 17 / 1-12)
  - Field Forces Bureau: Commander, 1999 (Box-folder 17 / 13-24)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Bureau Chief, 1999 (Box-folder 17 / 25-36)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 1999 (Box-folder 17 / 25-48)
  - Personnel Assistant, 1999 (Box-folder 17 / 49-60)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 2000 (Box-folder 16b / 37-40)
  - Personnel Assistant, 2000 (Box-folder 16b / 41-52)
  - Chief Administrator, 2000 (Box-folder 18 / 1-12)
  - Deputy Chief Administrator, 2000 (Box-folder 18 / 13-24)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Bureau Chief, 2000 (Box-folder 18 / 25-36)
  - Chief Administrator, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 1-12)
  - Deputy Chief Administrator, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 13-24)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 25-36)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Bureau Chief, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 37-48)
  - Personnel Assistant, 2001 (Box-folder 19 / 49-55)
  - Personnel Assistant, 2001 (Box-folder 20 / 1-5)
  - Chief Administrator, 2002 (Box-folder 20 / 6-15)
  - Deputy Chief Administrator, 2002 (Box-folder 20 / 16-27)
  - Administrative Commander, 2002 (Box-folder 20 / 28-35)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Training Officer, 2002 (Box-folder 20 / 36-47)
  - Training and Research Bureau: Bureau Chief, 2002 (Box-folder 20 / 48-56)
  - Personnel Assistant, 2002 (Box-folder 20a / 1-12)
  - Chief Administrator, 2003 (Box-folder 20a / 13-18)
  - Personnel Assistant, 2003 (Box-folder 20a / 19-24)
- Minutes
  - Detachment meetings, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 21 / 1-15)
  - Detachment meetings, 1998-2002 (Box-folder 22 / 1-8)
- Reports
  - A Study of Montana Highway Patrol Bureau Driver License Examiners as Opposed to Civil Examiners, 1973 (Box-folder 23 / 1)
- Subject Files
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Press cards, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 23 / 1)
  - Aerial enforcement, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 23 / 2)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Press releases, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 23 / 2-3)
  - American Association of Motor Vehicle Administrators, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 23 / 3)
  - American Legion, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 23 / 4)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Retirement board, 1958-1964 (Box-folder 23 / 4)
  - Armored motor services, 1968-1974 (Box-folder 23 / 5)
  - Court cases, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 23 / 6)
  - Federal agencies: Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1958-1970 (Box-folder 23 / 7)
  - Federal agencies: Dept. of Transportation, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 23 / 8)
  - Indian reservations, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 23 / 9)
  - International Association of Chiefs of Police, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 23 / 10-11)
  - Law Enforcement Teletype System, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 23 / 12)
  - Montana Association of Highway Patrolmen, 1954-1970 (Box-folder 23 / 13-14)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Attorney, 1957-1979 (Box-folder 23 / 15-19)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Board, 1962-1972 (Box-folder 23 / 20-21)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Captains, lieutenants, and sergeants, 1953-1976 (Box-folder 23 / 22-25)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Communications, 1968-1976 (Box-folder 23 / 26-27)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Organizational charts, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 23 / 28)
  - Montana Highway Patrol: Retirement system, 1972 (Box-folder 24 / 5)
  - Montana Motor Transport Association, 1958-1974 (Box-folder 24 / 6)
  - National Automobile Theft Bureau, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 24 / 7)
  - National Safety Council, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 24 / 8)
  - Northwestern University: Traffic Institute, 1958-1972 (Box-folder 24 / 9)
  - State agencies: Attorney general, 1959-1971 (Box-folder 24 / 10)
  - State agencies: Governor, 1962-1976 (Box-folder 24 / 11-16)
  - State agencies: Health, Dept. of, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 24 / 17)
  - State agencies: Highway Commission, 1963-1966 (Box-folder 24 / 18-21)
  - State agencies: Highway Commission, 1966-1971 (Box-folder 25 / 1-5)
  - State agencies: Highways, Dept. of, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 25 / 6-10)
  - State agencies: Highways, Dept. of, GVW, 1965-1976 (Box-folder 25 / 11-12)
  - State agencies: Secretary of State, 1963-1973 (Box-folder 25 / 13)
- Miscellany
  - List of school buses and school bus drivers, 1957 (Box-folder 25 / 14)